# Simon Holmbacka. PhD – Resume 19 June 2018

CONTACT Information Haagantie 62

20380 Turku, Finland Tel: +358 50 5310467

Email: sholmbac@abo.fi Gender: male

Time of birth: 24.01.1986

Place of birth: Jakobstad, Finland

Nationality: Finnish



May 2017 -

Position

AI Researcher

Elisa Oyj.

Task: Mobile network optimization using deep learning

Senior Researcher June 2017 –

University of Turku

Task: Creating MooCs for online education (25% contract)

EDUCATION

#### Åbo Akademi University, Finland

Doctor of Technology in Computer Engineering (26 Jan. 2016, Turku, Finland)

2011 - 2015

• Faculty: Science and Engineering

• Major: Embedded Computer Systems

• Minor: Software Engineering

• Minor: University Pedagogics

• Thesis: Energy-Aware Software for Many-Core Systems Grade: Honorary Grade

 $\bullet$ Reference: Prof. Johan Lilius johan.lilius@abo.fi

Master of Science in Computer Engineering (31 Mar. 2011, Turku, Finland)

2009 - 2011

• Institution: Information Technologies

• Major: Embedded Computer Systems

• Minor: Control Engineering

• Minor: Software Engineering

• Thesis: Task Migration in Virtualized Multi-Core Real-Time Systems Grade: 5/5

Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering (6 Oct. 2009, Turku, Finland)

2006 - 2009

• Institution: Information Technologies

• Major: Embedded Computer Systems

• Minor: Software Engineering

ABOUT ME

I come from the small city of Jakobstad in the mid west of Finland from which I moved to Turku to study computer engineering in 2006. I completed my Master's degree in 5 years (2006-2011) and my PhD in 4 years (2011-2015) from Åbo Akademi University in Turku, Finland.

Technical

I have worked extensively in the areas of embedded systems, runtime systems, power management and many-core platforms, which includes foremost low level system programming (usually in C), and lately I have been using Python more. Furthermore I have experience in other object oriented programming languages, mostly C++ and Java, and I have of course stumbled upon some Java script, xml and assembly programming. I have worked with system modeling, mathematical optimization and control theory including NLP optimization, digital filtering, plane fitting methods, control theory and its underlying mathematics. This means that I have very good knowledge of Matlab, its toolboxes and system simulation in Simulink. On the hardware side, I have excellent knowledge of ARM and Intel platforms in particular, and system/kernel programming using Linux. I have been hacking with the Linux kernel since I was 16 years old and know this world in and out. On further lower level I have worked with real-time operating systems like FreeRTOS during my PhD and I have also build many hobby projects from scratch using micro controllers such as an audio synthesizer complete with a midi interface and USB driver running on an 8-bit AVR. I am currently working with big data deep learning using Tensorflow/Keras and R, and optimization of deep learning models in Opentuner.

#### Project Work

In the 4 years of making my PhD I have published over 15 international peer reviewed scientific articles, one of which I received the best paper award for in 2014. I worked in the European FP-7 project RECOMP from 2011 - 2014 and in the national Tekes project ParallaX from 2014 - 2016, in which I worked together with universities and international IT companies like Wittenstein ltd., UK and Seven Solutions, Spain on programming and integration tasks. I am a very good team worker, which has shown in co-operations with 7 different universities in 4 countries during this time for my thesis, and outside of my thesis I have published work together with 12 different institutions and co-authored work together with over 30 people. I have visited more than 30 countries in my thesis work, and I find it very easy to join a team and start working on new projects with new people.

#### Languages

• Swedish: Mother tongue • Finnish: Conversational

• English: Fluent

• German: Conversational

#### Pedagogics

Education wise, I have been lecturing university courses in English since 2013 and completed university pedagogics as a minor subject. I created two online education MooCs on coursera.org from scratch in the EIT Digital project in 2015 – 2018, which are now freely available on Coursera and has thousands active students.

#### About Simon

I would describe myself as a person who takes the initiative, gets things started and gets things done. I have a very good working discipline with regard to time and responsibility, and I always do the work today instead of leaving it until tomorrow! I always start a task well on time, and I keep the promised timelines whether it is a question of delivering C code, an article, a presentation, course material or a PhD thesis.

My hobbies are traveling, gardening, skiing, hiking, driving, workout, watching airplanes and Trump-Russia investigation.

#### Teaching EXPERIENCE

# Course administrator: EIT Digital Online Coursera

Embedded Hardware and Operating Systems

2018

https://www.coursera.org/learn/embedded-operating-system/

Course creator: EIT Digital Online Coursera

Autonomous Runway Detection for IoT 2017

https://www.coursera.org/learn/embedded-systems-larger/

Course creator and lecturer: EIT Digital Online Coursera

Development of Real-Time Systems

2016

https://www.coursera.org/learn/real-time-systems/

Course lecturer: Real-Time Systems Åbo Akademi University	2012 - 2017
Advisor and examiner for thesis work: Åbo Akademi University	2012 - 2016
Prüfer für Abschlussarbeiten: FernUniversität in Hagen	2015 - 2016
Course assistant: Multimedia Algorithm Implementations Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2016
Course assistant: Multimedia Algorithm Implementations Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2013
Course assistant: Real-Time Systems Åbo Akademi University	Spring 2011

## Awards \*

## Elisa hackathon winner

Host: Elisa OYj

Rationale: Awarded first place for "Minder" - Tinder for movies app

## Researcher of the year

Host: Åbo Akademi University

Rationale: Awarded researcher of the year for of best PhD thesis during the year 2016

#### Best paper award

Host: Conference on Design & Architectures for Signal & Image Processing 2014

Rationale: Awarded best paper for work on power management system for multi-core processors

INVITED TALKS Development of MooCs and Digital Learning Location: Brussels, Belgium

Event: EIT Digital Conference 2017 Host: Martijn Klabbers, TU Eindhoven

PROGRAM The 26th Euromicro International Conference on Parallel, Distributed and Network-Based

Committees Processing, 2018

Location: Cambridge, UK

The tenth Nordic Workshop on Multi-Core Computing, 2017

Location: Uppsala, Sweden

RESEARCH VISITS Rennes 4 month research visit

Location: Rennes, France

Institution: Institut national des sciences appliquées de Rennes

Host: Maxime Pelcat, ITER Laboratory

Duration: November 2013 - March 2014

JOINT- Green Energy Cloud Simulation

COOPERATION Partners: Enida Sheme, Polytechnic University of Tirana, Tirana, Albania

Dražen Lučanin, TU Vienna, Vienna, Austria

Duration: August 15 - November 30 2015

**Energy Efficient Cloud Simulation** 

Partners: Dražen Lučanin, Ilia Pietri, Ivona Brandić, TU Vienna, Vienna, Austria

Duration: May 15 - May 30 2015

Power-Aware HEVC Decoding with Tunable Image Quality Partners: Erwan Nogues, Maxime Pelcat, INSA de Rennes, France

Duration: Winter 2014

Barrelfish port for Tilera Tile64

Partners: Xiaowen Wang, Robert Radkiewicz, Mats Brorsson, SICS, Stockholm, Sweden

Duration: Summer 2013

Task Migration Mechanism for Distributed Many-Core NoC Systems

Partners: Mohammad Fattah, Amir-Mohammad Rahmani, University of Turku, Finland

Duration: Spring 2013

Safe Motor Controller in Mixed-Critical Environment with Runtime Updating Capabilities

Partners: José Luis Gutiérrez, University of Granada, Spain

Miguel Méndez, Seven Solutions Inc., Spain

Duration: November 5 - November 17 2012

Safe Core-to-Core Channel Implementation

Partners: William Davy, Wittenstein Inc., UK

Duration: May 23 - May 24 2012

Grants Nvidia Grant 2018

For research on deep learning in telecommunications networks, GTX 1080 i

PoDoCo Grant (2.8% acceptance) 2017

For research on network optimization coordinated with Elisa Oyj, Helsinki, 28000€

Waldemar von Frenckells stiftelse 2016

For research on energy aware software, 5000€

Oskar Öflunds stiftelse 2016

For research co-operation with FernUniversität in Hagen, Germany, 3000€

Svenska tekniska vetenskapsakademien i Finland 2015

For research visit to FernUniversität in Hagen, Germany, 4500€

Otto Malms stiftelse 2014

For thesis on energy aware software, 5000€

Svenska tekniska vetenskapsakademien i Finland 2013

For research visit to Rennes, France, 2500€

Tekniikan edistämissäätiö 2013

For thesis on energy aware software, 5000€

Work Experience Elisa Oyj, Helsinki, Finland

IT Researcher

University of Turku, Turku, Finland

Senior researcher

Åbo Akademi University, Turku, Finland

Post-Doc Researcher

Fernuniversität in Hagen, Hagen, Germany

 $Wissenschaftlicher\ Mitarbeiter$ 

Åbo Akademi University, Turku, Finland

 $PhD\ Student$  Research assistant

Brisa Inc., Pedersöre, Finland

IT manager

Herrmans Inc., Pedersöre, Finland

IT support

Brisa Inc., Pedersöre, Finland

Webshop assistant

Digicomp Inc., Jakobstad, Finland

Sales person Technical support

Referees

Prof. Johan Lilius

Professor

Åbo Akademi University

Turku Finland

 ${\it phone: available \ on \ request}$ 

e-mail: johan.lilius@abo.fi

Prof. Jörg Keller

Professor

Fernuniversität in Hagen

Hagen Germany

phone: available on request

e-mail: joerg.keller@fernuni-hagen.de

May 2017 –

June 2017 -

January 2016 - April 2017

September 2015 - April 2017

March 2011 – December 2015

April 2010 - March 2011

May 2009 - September 2009

May 2008 - September 2008

May 2007 - September 2007

July 2006 – September 2006

May 2005 – January 2005

Kirsi Valtari

VP Telco Efficiency Business

Elisa Ovi

Helsinki Finland

phone: available on request e-mail: kirsi.valtari@elisa.fi

Prof. Juha Plosila

Professor

University of Turku Turku Finland

phone: available on request e-mail: juplos@utu.fi